

Guillaume Garrigos

Curriculum Vitae

Personal information and contact

- Born in Toulouse (France), May 8th 1989.
- ☐ Bâtiment Sophie Germain, Université de Paris, 75205 Paris CEDEX 13, France.
- @ guillaume.garrigos@lpsm.paris
- http://guillaume-garrigos.com

Current position (2018–)

position Maître de conférences at Université de Paris

affiliation Laboratoire de Probabilités, Statistique et Modélisation (LPSM, UMR 8001)

research optimization, statistical machine learning, inverse problems, image and signal pro-

interests cessing, algorithms and continuous dynamical systems, tame optimization.

Previous positions (2015–2018)

2017–2018 **Post-doc**, École Normale Supérieure, Paris, France.

Lab: Département de Mathématiques et Applications Main collaborator : Gabriel Peyré (ENS, CNRS, INRIA)

Research themes: inverse problems, signal and image processing, optimization

2015–2017 **Post-doc**, *Istituto Italiano di Tecnologia*, Genoa, Italy.

Lab: Laboratory for Computational and Statistical Learning

Main collaborators: Lorenzo Rosasco (IIT, MIT) and Silvia Villa (IIT)

Research themes: optimization and regularization methods for machine learning.

Ph.D. thesis (2012–2015)

title Descent dynamical systems and algorithms for tame optimization and multi-objective problems

university Université de Montpellier (France) and Universidad Santa Maria (Valparaíso, Chile)

supervisors Hédy Attouch (UM) and Juan Peypouquet (USM)

committee Hédy Attouch, Aris Daniilidis, Jalal Fadili, Pedro Gajardo, Adrian Lewis, Juan Peypouquet, Lionel Thibault

Education and Degrees

- 2013 Agrégation de Mathématiques, ranked 147/323.
- 2010–2012 **Master**, *Université de Montpellier*. Mathématiques, Statistiques et Applications
- 2007–2010 **Licence**, *Université de Montpellier*. Mathématiques Fondamentales et Appliquées
 - 2007 Baccalauréat, Lycée Diderot, Narbonne.

Publications

Publications in international specialized journals.

- o G. Garrigos, L. Rosasco and S. Villa. *Accelerated iterative regularization via dual diagonal descent*, SIAM Journal on Optimization, Vol. 31, No. 1, pp. 754–784, 2021.
- G. Garrigos, L. Rosasco and S. Villa. *Thresholding gradient methods in Hilbert spaces:* support identification and linear convergence, ESAIM: Control, Optimisation and Calculus of Variations, Vol. 26 (28), 2020.
- o G. Garrigos, L. Rosasco and S. Villa. *Iterative regularization via dual diagonal descent*, Journal of Mathematical Imaging and Vision, Vol. 60, No. 2, pp. 189–215, 2018.
- o G. Garrigos, L. Rosasco and S. Villa. *Convergence of the Forward-Backward algorithm:* beyond the worst case with geometry, Mathematical Programming, to appear, 2022.
- H. Attouch, G. Garrigos and X. Goudou. A dynamic gradient approach to Pareto optimization with nonsmooth convex objective functions, Journal of Mathematical Analysis and Applications, Vol. 422, No. 1, pp. 741–771, 2015.
- o P. Frankel, G. Garrigos and J. Peypouquet. *Splitting methods with variable metric for KL functions and general convergence rates*, Journal of Optimization Theory and Applications, Vol. 165, No. 3, pp. 874–900, 2015. ☐

Publications in international conferences.

- o J. Chen, R. Yuan, G. Garrigos and R. M. Gower. *SAN: Stochastic Average Newton Algorithm for Minimizing Finite Sums*, 25th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), PMLR, Vol. 151, pp. 279–318, 2022.
- o G. Garrigos, L. Rosasco and S. Villa. Sparse Multiple Kernel Learning: Support Identification via Mirror Stratifiability, IEEE 26th European Signal Processing Conference (EUSIPCO), pp. 1077–1081, 2018.
- J. Fadili, G. Garrigos, J. Malick and G. Peyré. Model Consistency for Learning with Mirror-Stratifiable Regularizers, 22nd International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), PMLR, Vol. 89, pp. 1236–1244, 2019.
- o G. Garrigos, L. Rosasco and S. Villa. *Iterative regularization via a dual diagonal descent method*, 9th NIPS Workshop on Optimization for Machine Learning, 2016.

Preprints.

• H. Attouch and G. Garrigos. *Multiobjective optimization*: an inertial dynamical approach to Pareto optima. Preprint on arXiv:1506.02823.

Teaching

2022-2023 Mathématiques 1, CM-TD, L1, 45h
Optimization for Machine Learning, CM, M2, 36h
Calcul Différentiel, TD, L3, 36h

2018-2019 Optimisation, TD, L3, 36h
Théorie de l'Information, TD, M1, 36h
Analyse Numérique Matricielle, TD-TP, L3, 54h

2016-2017 Machine Learning, TP, M, 8h (Part of the RegML 2017 Summer School) •

2014-2015 Algèbre Linéaire, CM-TD, L1, 128h2012-2013 Algèbre Linéaire, CM-TD, L1, 64h

Miscellaneous

- 2019 PEPS grant funded by INSMI (CNRS), 3,5k EUR.
- 2017 SMAI-MODE Dodu Prize for the best young researcher talk: Structured sparsity in inverse problems and support recovery with mirror-stratifiable functions.

Responsibilities

Seminars, Events

- 2019 Co-organizer of the workshop "Regularisation for Inverse Problems and Machine Learning", in Paris

 Output

 Description:
- 2018 Co-organizer of the session "Dimensionality reduction tools for learning: A sketchy session" for the International Symposium on Mathematical Programming (ISMP)
- 2017 Organizer of the NORIA group meeting at ENS
- 2017 Co-organizer of the Machine Learning summer school RegML 2017, in Oslo 😣
- 2015–2017 Organizer of the Machine Learning Tutorials, between the LCSL groups at IIT (Genova) and MIT (Boston)

Editorial Activity

I am reviewing for various journals: SIAM Journal on Optimization, SIAM Journal on Imaging Science, Mathematics of Operations Research, Optimization, Mathematical Methods of Operations Research, Journal of Optimization Theory and Applications, Computational and Applied Mathematics, IEEE Computational Intelligence Magazine.

List of given talks

- o 2022-07-30 Journées Franco-Chiliennes d'Optimisation. Perpignan, France.
- o 2022-06-01 Groupe de Travail Réseaux de Neurones. Université Paris Cité, Paris, France.
- o 2022-05-16 Seminar. Center for Computational Mathematics, Simons Foundation, New York, U.S.A..
- o 2019-12-04 Journées PGMO. Palaiseau, France.
- o 2019-11-28 SMILE Seminar. ENS, Paris, France.
- o 2019-08-07 ICCOPT. Technical University, Berlin, Germany.
- o 2019-06-21 Séminaire Modélisation, Optimisation, Dynamique . XLIM, Limoges, France.
- o 2019-05-22 Machine Learning Seminar. LCSL, Genova, Italy.
- o 2019-05-13 Biennale de la SMAI. Guidel, France.
- o 2019-04-17 AISTATS. Okinawa, Japan.
- o 2019-03-21 Groupe de Travail Modélisation. LPSM, Paris, France.
- o 2019-02-21 Science communication. Université de Paris, Paris, France.
- o 2019-02-18 Séminaire Parisien de Statistique. IHP, Paris, France.
- o 2019-02-14 Séminaire d'Analyse non linéaire et Optimisation. LMA, Avignon, France.
- o 2018-09-03 European Signal Processing Conference (EUSIPCO). Roma, Italy.
- o 2018-07-01 International Symposium on Mathematical Programming (ISMP). IMB, Bordeaux, France.
- o 2018-06-05 SIAM Conference on Imaging Science. Bologna, Italy.
- o 2018-05-21 Inverse Problems: Modeling and Simulation conference. Malta, Malta.
- o 2018-05-05 Journée Parcimonie et Applications du GdR MIA. IMB, Bordeaux, France.
- o 2018-04-16 Séminaire Signal, Statistique et Apprentissage. Telecom, Paris, France.
- o 2018-03-28 Journées SMAI-MODE. Grenoble, France.
- o 2018-02-20 Séminaire commun de Statistique P6-P7. Paris Diderot, Paris, France.
- o 2018-02-07 Séminaire Images Optimisation et Probabilités. IMB, Bordeaux, France.
- o 2018-01-29 Machine Learning Seminar. LCSL, Genova, Italy.
- o 2018-01-23 Séminaire du Centre de Vision Numérique. Centrale Supélec, Paris, France.
- o 2018-01-15 Mathematics and Image Analysis conference. Humboldt University, Berlin, Germany.
- o 2017-12-14 Workshop on Dynamics and Algorithms in Convex Optimization. Universidad de Chile, Santiago, Chile.
- o 2017-12-11 V-Coloquio. Pontifica Universidad Catolica de Valparaiso, Valparaiso, Chile.
- o 2017-12-07 Séminaire LJK-Probabilités et Statistique. LJK, Grenoble, France.
- o 2017-11-18 Workshop on Gradient dynamics, convergence and related topics. UPMC, Paris, France.
- o 2017-10-17 Journées du GDR MOA-MIA. IMB, Bordeaux, France.
- o 2017-10-17 Optimization 2017. Lisboa, Portugal.
- o 2017-07-05 Journées Franco-Chiliennes d'Optimisation. IMT, Toulouse, France.
- o 2017-02-14 Séminaire SIERRA. INRIA, Paris, France.
- o 2017-02-09 Séminaire Mathématiques de l'apprentissage. IMT, Toulouse, France.
- o 2016-12-19 Seminario del Departamento de Matematica. Universidad Santa Maria, Valparaiso, Chile.
- o 2016-12-14 Seminar of Optimization and Equilibrium. CMM, Santiago, Chile.
- o 2016-12-10 NIPS. Barcelona, Spain.
- o 2016-08-09 ICCOPT. Tokyo, Japan.
- o 2016-03-23 Journées SMAI-MODE. Toulouse, France.
- o 2016-02-08 Séminaire SPOT. Toulouse, France.
- o 2015-12-02 Journées annuelles du GdR MOA. Université de Bourgogne, Dijon, France.
- 2015-07-14 International Symposium on Mathematical Programming. Pittsburgh, USA.
- o 2015-03-04 Séminaire Statistiques, Probabilités, Optimisation et Contrôle. Université de Bourgogne, Dijon, France.
- o 2014-12-04 Encuentro anual de la Sociedad Matematica de Chile (SOMATCHI). Quinamavida, Chile.
- o 2014-10-30 Seminario del Departamento de Matematica. Universidad Santa Maria, Valparaiso, Chile.
- o 2014-09-08 Franco-Italian Workshop. LCSL, Sestri-Levante, Italia.
- o 2014-09-02 Séminaire ACSIOM. IMAG, Montpellier, France.
- o 2014-03-26 Journées SMAI-MODE. Rennes, France.

- o 2013-12-12 Seminario DMAT. Universidad Santa Maria, Valparaiso, Chile.
- o 2013-09-25 Seminar of Optimization and Equilibrium. CMM, Santiago, Chile.
- o 2013-06-17 Journées annuelles du GdR MOA. IHP, Paris, France.